Haru...
Haru...
I followed your scent and managed to get here,
Aku ikuti baumu dan berhasil ke sini,
but it is impossible to follow your scent here anymore.
kini mustahil mengikuti baumu di sini lagi.
The only clue I have is "Shishi-Gumi."
Petunjuk yang kudapatkan hanya "Shishi-Gumi."
Hey, dude, what's the matter with you? Want some goat arms?
Hei, kenapa kau? Mau lengan kambing?
Excuse me. Do you know anything about Shishi-Gumi?
Maaf. Kau tahu soal Shishi-Gumi?
Shi...
Shi...
No, you didn't tell me anything.
Tidak, kau tak beri tahu apa-apa.
Excuse me, is Shishi-Gumi...
Maaf, apa Shishi-Gumi...
Once they hear me say "Shishi-Gumi,"
Setelah mereka dengar kukatakan "Shishi-Gumi,"
they just run away or look away from me.
mereka kabur atau berpaling dariku.
What should I do?
Aku harus bagaimana?
Hey, watch where you're going.
Hei, lihat jalanmu.
Oh, I'm sorry...
Maaf...
Do you know where Shishi-Gumi is?
Kau tahu di mana Shishi-Gumi?
-Shishi-Gumi? -Yes.
- Shishi-Gumi? - Ya.
This way.
Lewat sini.
Are they somewhere around here?
Apa mereka di sekitar sini?
You will just die in vain if you go to Shishi-Gumi.
Kau akan mati sia-sia jika menemui Shishi-Gumi.
Why don't you let us skin your fur off instead?
Kenapa kau tak biarkan kami menguliti bulumu saja?
Let's see...
Mari lihat...
Is this all you have?
Kau cuma punya ini?
My friend was abducted by Shishi-Gumi.
Temanku diculik Shishi-Gumi.
Your wallet is totally empty.
Dompetmu kosong melompong.
We can't sell your fur if they sank you in the pond.
Kami tak bisa jual bulumu jika kau ditenggelamkan di empang.
The pond?
Empang?
Young wolf fur fetches a high price--
Bulu serigala muda harganya tinggi...
Thanks for taking care of my patient.
Terima kasih sudah mengurus pasienku.
Damn. Let's get out of here.
Sial. Ayo pergi.
Panda.
Panda.
My name is Gohin, not Panda.
Namaku Gohin, bukan Panda.
Even carnivores are preyed around here. Keep that in mind.
Bahkan karnivora diburu di sini. Ingat itu.
Well, I want to go to the Shishi-Gumi's hideout.
Aku ingin ke tempat persembunyian Shishi-Gumi.
Hey, keep your voice down.
Hei, pelankan suaramu.
Listen,
Begini,
Shishi-Gumi is a criminal organization consisting of 35 lions.
Shishi-Gumi adalah organisasi kejahatan berisi 35 singa.
A dangerous group that devours herbivores as a business.
Kelompok berbahaya yang melahap herbivora sebagai bisnis.
Even I don't want to deal with them.
Bahkan aku tak mau hadapi mereka.
What can a single wolf do...
Apa yang bisa dilakukan satu serigala...
All right. I understand.
Baik. Aku paham.
SHISHI-GUMI
SHISHI-GUMI
Where is the pond, anyway?
Di mana empangnya?
Were you even listening to me?
Apa kau dengarkan aku?
I have no idea what this is for, but you'll be killed.
Aku tak tahu apa masalahnya, tetapi kau akan terbunuh.
Well, yeah, that seems possible from what you've just told me.
Ya, itu tampaknya mungkin dari penjelasanmu.
But the rabbit girl I was talking about has been abducted by them.
Tetapi gadis kelinci yang kuceritakan diculik oleh mereka.
Sorry to hear that, but there's nothing you can do about it.
Aku prihatin mendengarnya, tetapi kau tak bisa apa-apa.
She must have already been devoured.
Dia pasti sudah dilahap.
I have to save her, no matter what.
Aku harus menyelamatkannya, bagaimanapun caranya.
I have to make up for what I've done to her as a carnivore.
Aku harus menebus perbuatanku kepadanya sebagai karnivora.
That I tried to eat her when I met her for the first time,
Bahwa aku coba memakannya saat pertama kali kami bertemu,
and I, such a jerk wolf,
dan aku, serigala berengsek,
am in love with her.
jatuh cinta kepadanya.
If I could still survive after I made up for the sin,
Jika aku masih hidup setelah menebus dosa,
I want to tell her my feelings.
aku ingin ungkapkan perasaanku.
Well, maybe I can't.
Mungkin aku tak bisa.
This is ridiculous.
Ini konyol.
It's okay if you won't tell me where the pond is.
Tak apa-apa jika kau tak mau beri tahu di mana empang itu.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Hey. Wait.
Hei. Tunggu.
That stupid brat...
Bocah bodoh itu...
Who cares.
Siapa peduli.
It's raining so hard.
Hujan deras.
We can't go back to school.
Kita tak bisa kembali ke sekolah.
I wonder where Legoshi is.
Entah ke mana Legoshi.
-He didn't take his stuff with him. -Yeah.
- Dia tak bawa barangnya. - Ya.
Look at Rouis.
Lihat Rouis.
Hey, he may hear you.
Hei, dia mungkin mendengarmu.
Rouis.
Rouis.
What happened between you and Legoshi?
Apa yang terjadi antara kau dan Legoshi?
Why?
Kenapa?
If you think I'm not aware of anything, you are very wrong.
Jika kau kira aku tak tahu apa-apa, kau salah besar.
I was freaked out when I found out that he loves her, though.
Aku panik saat tahu dia mencintai Haru.
Where has he gone?
Legoshi pergi ke mana?
I don't think we'll see him again.
Kurasa kita tak akan melihatnya lagi.
I'm seriously asking--
Aku serius bertanya...
I am serious, too.
Aku juga serius.
Does it have something to do with the rabbit?
Apa itu berkaitan dengan si kelinci?
Sorry, Juno...
Maaf, Juno...
I couldn't prevent anything.
Aku tak bisa mencegah apa pun.
Tonight, he might get killed.
Malam ini, mungkin dia akan terbunuh.
I don't think I can get through the front gate.
Kurasa aku tak bisa melalui gerbang depan.
What should I do?
Aku harus bagaimana?
It's unusual to see a wolf visiting here alone.
Janggal melihat serigala berkunjung ke sini sendirian.
I thought wolves could only act in a pack.
Kukira serigala hanya bertindak dengan kawanan.
Trespassing is not allowed,
Masuk tanpa izin dilarang,
whether it's for vengeance or for selling something.
baik untuk balas dendam atau menjual sesuatu.
Please... let me explain.
Kumohon, biar aku jelaskan.
-I have a reason to be here-- -No, no, no.
- Aku punya alasan ada di sini... - Tidak.
Don't deprive me of such a great opportunity.
Jangan cegah aku untuk mendapat peluang hebat.
We, the Felidae,
Kami, Felidae,
are absolutely sick of you, Canidae.
muak dengan kalian, Canidae.
Even though you guys are as ferocious as we are,
Walau kalian sebuas kami,
your friendliness with your tails wagging gets on our nerves.
keramahan kalian dengan ekor mengibas membuat kami kesal.
What a great reward for me to be able to shoot their symbol,
Aku sangat puas jika bisa menembak lambang mereka,
a gray wolf. That's something I never expected.
serigala kelabu. Hal itu tak pernah kuperkirakan.
Do you have any last words?
Kau punya ucapan terakhir?
It's coming in.
Ini datang.
I can see it.
Aku bisa melihatnya.
It can't be... No, I'm definitely sure...
Tak mungkin... Tidak, aku yakin...
He's touched Haru.
Dia menyentuh Haru.
What have you done to her?
Apa yang kau lakukan padanya?
I see, so you're here to save that rabbit.
Aku paham, kau ke sini untuk selamatkan kelinci itu.
She's on the top floor of the building.
Dia di lantai teratas gedung ini.
But it's kinda too late.
Tetapi agak terlambat.
If you want to see her, you must make him vomit.
Jika kau mau melihat si kelinci, kau harus buat dia muntah.
You can still see her if she hasn't been digested yet.
Kau masih bisa melihatnya jika dia belum dicerna.
STUDENT ID - NAME: ELS CLASSIFICATION: ALPACA
KARTU PELAJAR - NAMA: ELS PENGGOLONGAN: ALPACA
You, old man. Tell me the truth.
Kau, Pria Tua. Katakan sejujurnya.
I don't smell blood from you.
Aku tak cium darah darimu.
Her blood. So, she should still be alive.
Darahnya. Jadi, dia masih hidup.
No. I didn't...
Tidak. Aku tidak...
I know.
Aku tahu.
I know the smell of her blood.
Aku tahu bau darahnya.
Haru is mine.
Haru milikku.
Haru is my prey...
Haru adalah mangsaku...
What?
Apa?
My prey?
Mangsaku?
Don't mess with me.
Jangan main-main denganku.
Bastard, I'll kill you.
Berengsek, kubunuh kau.
Well, it's probably a perfect day for hunting those cats today.
Mungkin hari ini sempurna untuk berburu para kucing itu.
Mr. Gohin...
Tn. Gohin...
Why didn't you bite him?
Kenapa kau tak menggigitnya?
The only way to defeat those Felidae soldiers for a wolf like you
Cara mengalahkan prajurit Felidae itu untuk serigala sepertimu
is to bite them
adalah menggigit mereka
using your jaw.
menggunakan rahangmu.
I shouldn't...
Aku tak boleh
bite anyone because I just had...
menggigit siapa pun karena aku baru...
You're so helpless.
Kau sungguh payah.
Who would risk his own life just to make a love confession?
Siapa yang membahayakan jiwanya untuk bisa mengakui cinta?
Listen, don't hesitate to bite next time.
Lain kali jangan ragu-ragu menggigit.
Bite in the neck.
Gigit di leher.
Even though your love is originated from your hunting instinct,
Walau cintamu diawali dari naluri berburumu,
you believe your act can change the outcome, right?
kau yakin tindakanmu bisa mengubah hasilnya, bukan?
Here.
Ayo.
Don't run away.
Jangan kabur.
Righteous acts are worth it,
Tindakan yang benar itu layak,
but it's really rough.
tetapi sangat sulit.
I know. I have no choice.
Aku tahu. Aku tak ada pilihan.
Or I would be like just one of these guys.
Atau aku akan menjadi seperti mereka.
That's right.
Benar.
Tame the beast inside you, Legoshi.
Jinakkan naluri buas dalam dirimu, Legoshi.
That's what a mature man is supposed to do in this world.
Begitulah yang harus dilakukan pria dewasa di dunia ini.
Take this.
Terima ini.
SHISHI
SHISHI
Who the hell are you?
Siapa kau?
You bastard.
Kau berengsek.
Such a jerk, you know?
Dasar bajingan.
Mr. Gohin.
Tn. Gohin.
Legoshi, hurry, go upstairs.
Legoshi, cepat, naiklah.
You, old man.
Kau, Pria Tua.
One more.
Sekali lagi.
He's aiming at my nose.
Dia mengincar hidungku.
Are you surprised that I know the bear's muzzle is full of nerves?
Kau heran aku tahu moncong beruang itu penuh saraf?
Legoshi...
Legoshi...
Get out of my way, bastard.
Menyingkir, Berengsek.
He's just a kid. Is he a friend of that rabbit?
Dia masih kecil. Apa dia teman kelinci itu?
I can make you feel comfortable soon.
Aku segera bisa membuatmu nyaman.
I can kill you with my hands that abducted the rabbit.
Aku bisa membunuhmu dengan tanganku yang menculik kelinci.
What?
Apa?
The scent is still fresh.
Baunya masih segar.
Haru...
Haru...
I know you're still alive.
Aku tahu kau masih hidup.
Damn, you're so creepy. Take this.
Sial, kau sangat menakutkan. Terima ini.
I miss you.
Aku merindukanmu.
Hey. Are you doped--
Hei. Apa kau teler...
The scent stimulates all the muscles of my body
Bau itu merangsang semua otot tubuhku
and heats my body up
dan memanaskan tubuhku
because I feel you in the scent.
karena aku merasakanmu dalam bau itu.
My simple ego, which makes me stronger than instinct.
Ego sederhana yang membuatku lebih kuat daripada naluri.
I'm coming to see you.
Aku datang untuk menemuimu.
Legoshi, you can leave him to me. Go upstairs now.
Legoshi, kau bisa biarkan dia untukku. Naiklah ke lantai atas.
But...
Tetapi...
I can beat these small fry up all by myself.
Aku bisa kalahkan begundal kecil sendiri.
Don't die.
Jangan mati.
I won't. You, too, Mr. Gohin.
Tak akan. Kau juga, Tn. Gohin.
Such a smart-ass.
Dasar sok tahu.
TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN
UNTUK YANG BERKEPENTINGAN
Wait. Do I need to begin with "To whom it may concern"?
Tunggu. Apa kau harus memulai dengan "Untuk yang berkepentingan"?
What does that even mean?
Apa artinya?
Oh, it's just a kind of greeting, huh?
Oh, itu semacam salam, ya?
Well, forget it.
Lupakanlah.
I don't care who's going to read it.
Aku tak peduli siapa yang akan baca.
A farewell note beginning with a greeting is just too gloomy.
Surat perpisahan yang dimulai dengan salam itu terlalu menyedihkan.
This is more like...
Ini lebih berupa,
a review of my life instead of a farewell note.
tinjauan kehidupanku alih-alih surat perpisahan.
It's like I'm intentionally having a flashback.
Ibarat aku sengaja alami kilas balik.
I AM DYING WITHIN MINUTES
AKU SEKARAT BEBERAPA MENIT LAGI
My life is...
Kehidupanku
ending so miserably that it's almost funny.
berakhir begitu mengenaskan hingga hampir lucu.
I was abducted by a weird group.
Aku diculik oleh kelompok aneh.
And I'm being inspected to see my quality as meat.
Aku diperiksa untuk melihat mutuku sebagai daging.
It's too late to give an excuse,
Terlambat untuk memberi alasan,
but as a female and a small animal,
tetapi sebagai betina dan hewan kecil,
I was just desperate to live my life.
aku putus asa untuk menjalani hidupku.
I really was.
Sungguh.
But the way I lived my life
Tetapi caraku menjalani hidupku
probably led to this ending.
mungkin mengarah pada akhir ini.
Since I was born as a dwarf rabbit,
Sejak aku dilahirkan sebagai kelinci kerdil,
how could I expect a happy life?
bagaimana aku bisa mengharapkan hidup bahagia?
I was born in a typical dwarf rabbit's family
Aku dilahirkan dalam keluarga kelinci kerdil biasa
and raised with my parents' love, just like other animals.
dan dibesarkan dengan cinta orang tuaku, seperti hewan lain.
Because I was the tiniest among my siblings,
Karena aku yang terkecil di antara saudaraku,
my parents always told me...
orang tuaku selalu berkata...
Always be cautious.
Selalu berhati-hati.
Dwarf rabbits are one of the weakest herbivores.
Kelinci kerdil salah satu herbivora yang paling lemah.
So, you have to be careful.
Jadi, kau harus hati-hati.
Why?
Kenapa?
Because you can die easily.
Karena kau bisa mati dengan mudah.
It didn't go down well with me when I was little,
Tak berhasil baik bagiku saat aku masih kecil,
but I began to understand what that meant when I turned ten years old.
tetapi aku mulai paham apa maknanya saat usiaku sepuluh tahun.
Here, let me help you.
Ini, biar kubantu.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
No matter how old I was,
Berapa pun usiaku,
all other animals treated me like a baby.
semua hewan lain memperlakukanku seperti anak kecil.
Why are you smiling?
Kenapa kau tersenyum?
Nothing. Thanks.
Tak apa-apa. Terima kasih.
Because I am small, fragile,
Karena aku kecil, rentan,
miserable,
sengsara,
and I can die easily.
dan aku bisa mudah mati.
Everybody smiles at such a pitiful animal.
Semua tersenyum kepada hewan yang malang.
-Oh, sorry. -Aren't you hurt?
- Maaf. - Kau tak sakit?
You don't have to carry this, Haru.
Kau tak harus membawa ini, Haru.
I grew up as others were giving me "poor you" smiles.
Aku tumbuh ketika yang lain memberiku senyuman "kasihan kau."
It was when I was in eighth grade.
Itu saat aku kelas delapan.
I... I've been...
Aku...
in love with you.
jatuh cinta kepadamu.
Would you be my girlfriend?
Apa kau mau jadi pacarku?
He's not smiling.
Dia tak tersenyum.
I finally found it.
Akhirnya kutemukan.
The only moment
Satu-satunya saat
I can be equal to other animals.
aku bisa setara dengan hewan lain.
In that moment, I was not "a poor rabbit."
Pada saat itu, aku bukan "kelinci malang."
I was not treated as a weakling. There's no lies in the bed.
Aku tak diperlakukan sebagai hewan lemah. Tak ada kebohongan di ranjang.
I wanted someone to see me as Haru,
Aku ingin orang memandangku sebagai Haru,
not as a fragile dwarf rabbit.
bukan kelinci kerdil yang rentan.
Haru, are you all right?
Haru, kau baik-baik saja?
What?
Apa?
It may sound strange,
Mungkin terdengar aneh,
but I felt like I was recognized just the way I was for the first time.
tetapi aku merasa dikenali sebagaimana diriku untuk pertama kalinya.
Even though I've lost friends, and they looked down on me,
Walau aku kehilangan teman, dan mereka meremehkanku,
strangely,
anehnya,
it felt a lot more comfortable than being pitied.
aku merasa jauh lebih nyaman dibanding dikasihani.
But it's over now.
Tetapi kini usai.
It's over.
Sudah usai.
It's time to say goodbye
Saatnya mengucapkan selamat tinggal
to the trashy 18 years of a dumb dwarf rabbit.
kepada kelinci kerdil bodoh murahan berusia 18 tahun.
I couldn't tell my true feelings to the boy I really loved.
Aku tak bisa ungkapkan perasaan asliku kepada pemuda yang kucintai.
I still don't know what I was born to do and my value.
Aku masih tak tahu untuk apa aku dilahirkan dan apa nilaiku.
All I have... are regrets.
Yang kumiliki, hanya penyesalan.
I...
Aku...
Why?
Kenapa?
Why is Legoshi here?
Kenapa Legoshi di sini?
He is not sociable, and he doesn't talk much.
Dia tak ramah, dan tak banyak bicara.
I never know what he's thinking.
Aku tak pernah tahu pemikirannya.
But this gray wolf boy has always been straightforward with me.
Tetapi pemuda serigala kelabu ini selalu berterus terang kepadaku.
You have never pitied me
Kau tak pernah mengasihaniku
or showed compassion to me,
atau menunjukkan belas kasih kepadaku,
but you always saw me for who I am.
tetapi kau selalu memandangku apa adanya.
You're so weird.
Kau sangat aneh.
That's right.
Benar.
I'm gonna get killed anyway,
Aku akan tetap dibunuh,
so I want you to be proud of me in the end.
maka aku ingin kau bangga denganku pada akhirnya.
Humiliation and shame stir the blood,
Penghinaan dan malu membuat darahmu mendidih,
and it makes you taste even better.
dan itu membuatmu terasa lebih lezat.
Hey, old man.
Hei, Kakek.
Excuse me, but I was busy writing a farewell note in my head
Maaf, tetapi aku sibuk menulis surat perpisahan di kepalaku
while you were bragging about yourself.
selagi kau menyombongkan diri.
Humiliation stirs the blood and makes me taste better?
Penghinaan membuat darah mendidih dan membuatku lebih lezat?
Unfortunately, I am very calm now.
Sayangnya, aku sangat tenang saat ini.
I heard you're a gourmet.
Kudengar kau suka hidangan lezat, ya?
Sorry that I ruined your dinner.
Maaf aku merusak makan malammu.
You're gonna have to eat the tough meat of a not-humiliated and unashamed female.
Kau harus makan daging keras betina yang tak malu dan tak tahu diri.
Old man.
Kakek.
Come on! Eat me now. I'm just getting less flavorful.
Ayo! Makan aku sekarang. Aku cuma jadi kurang lezat.
I'm ready!
Aku siap!
Looks like I've been too generous to you.
Tampaknya aku terlalu dermawan bagimu.
I would not eat tough meat.
Aku tak mau makan daging keras.
I will humiliate you with all my heart.
Aku akan mempermalukanmu habis-habisan.
No.
Tidak.
Let's start with your ears.
Ayo mulai dengan telingamu.
No. Let go of me!
Tidak. Lepaskan aku!
I'm so alone... even at the end.
Aku sangat sendirian, bahkan pada akhir hidupku.
Nobody is gonna come to save me.
Tak ada yang akan menyelamatkanku.
Nobody...
Tak ada...
My life is over now.
Kini hidupku berakhir.
Legoshi...
Legoshi...
Behind you.
Di belakangmu.
Sorry if it stinks.
Maaf jika ini bau.
Put my shirt on.
Pakai bajuku.
Why are you here?
Kenapa kau di sini?
I have too many reasons to tell you now.
Ada terlalu banyak alasan untuk kukatakan.
Are you stupid?
Apa kau bodoh?
A WOLF IN SHEEP'S CLOTHING
SERIGALA BERBULU DOMBA
Subtitle translation by Kanako Murakoshi
Terjemahan subtitle oleh Mimi Larasati Bonnetto